<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cooking Analytics</title>
    <description>This blog is focused on Analytics solutions, providing architectural and development recipes that can be applied to traditional Business Analytics solutions or applied to some hot topics like Big Data, IoT and Social Innovation solutions.</description>
    <link>http://mfgaspar.github.io/index.html//</link>
    <atom:link href="http://mfgaspar.github.io/index.html//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2016 21:57:07 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2016 21:57:07 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Learning Pentaho Ctools</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Pentaho and Ctools are two of the fastest and most rapidly growing tools for practical solutions not found in any other tool available on the market. Using Pentaho allows you to build a complete analytics solution, and Ctools brings an advanced flexibility to customizing them in a remarkable way. Ctools provides its users with the ability to utilize Web technologies and data visualization concepts, and make the most of best practices to create a huge visual impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cover was already released: 
&lt;img src=&quot;http://mfgaspar.github.io/assets/B04770_BookCover_small.png&quot; alt=&quot;Learning Pentaho Ctools Cover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;book-overview&quot;&gt;Book Overview&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book starts with the basics of the framework and how to get data to your dashboards. We’ll take you all the way through to create your custom and advanced dashboards that will create an effective visual impact and provide the best user experience. You will be given deep insights into the lifecycle of dashboards and the working of various components. Further, you will create a custom dashboard using the Community Dashboards Editor and use datasources to load data on the components. You will also create custom content using Query, the Freeform Addins Popup, and text components. Next, you will make use of widgets to create similar sections and duplicate components to reproduce other components on a dashboard. You will then learn to build a plugin without writing Java code, use Sparkl as a CPK plugin manager, and understand the application of deployment and version control to dashboard development. Finally, you will learn tips and tricks that can be very useful while embedding dashboards into other applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide is an invaluable tutorial if you are planning to use custom and advanced dashboards among the solutions that you are building with Pentaho.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-you-will-learn&quot;&gt;What You Will Learn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Install Community Tools on Pentaho; and understand the necessary concepts and considerations when creating an exciting dashboard design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get data from many different Pentaho datasources and deliver it in different formats (CSV, XLS, XML, or JSON)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use the Community Data Access (CDA) as the data abstraction layer and understand the concepts in the Community Dashboard Framework (CDF)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a Community Dashboard Editor (CDE) dashboard and make the most of the main components&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create and make use of widgets and use duplicate components to have data-driven sections on the dashboard&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Customize and create interaction between all components, including charts, using the Community Charts Components&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create and embed dashboards in a better and new way&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a Pentaho plugin using the Community App Builder&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create plugins and make use of parameters inside Pentaho without writing code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;who-this-book-is-for&quot;&gt;Who This Book Is For&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a Ctools developer and would like to expand your knowledge and create attractive dashboards and frameworks, this book is the go-to-guide for you. A basic knowledge of JavaScript and Cascading Style Sheets (CSS) is highly recommended. Definitly a knowledege on Pentaho is a requirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.packtpub.com/big-data-and-business-intelligence/learning-pentaho-ctools&quot;&gt;Packt&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Learning-Pentaho-Ctools-Miguel-Gaspar-ebook/dp/B0171UHJJ6/&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was exepect to be out at the end of this month, but since tomorrow is the last ady of the month, It will get a bit delayed :(&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any questions please send email or contact me over &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/miguel.ferreira.gaspar&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/migfgaspar&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/mfgaspar&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2016 20:15:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://mfgaspar.github.io/index.html//2016/Ctools-Book/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mfgaspar.github.io/index.html//2016/Ctools-Book/</guid>
        
        <category>Pentaho Ctools Book</category>
        
        
        <category>Pentaho Ctools Book</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to Cooking Analytics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I hope you can find this Blog interesting, where you will be able to read about Analytics solutions bringing architecture discussions, development technics that can be aplied to Big Data solutions, IoT or Social Innovation solutions, most of the time focused in Pentaho.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also make some post that will point to some interesting links, and that I believe it might bring value to the tiopics being discussed, and based on the feedback I might get from readers. Together we might do this Blog better!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me also apologise for the poor English that you might find in the posts, it’s getting better day-by-day but still far away from desired!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will try to complement the text with images and videos as mutch as I can. Not sure I will be able to add a section for comments, but will investigate how it can it be done using this or another theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, I would prefer to use twitter, facebook for comments, discussions, … and contributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Send me an email if it’s a private comment or question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking foward to get feedback from you!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2016 20:05:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://mfgaspar.github.io/index.html//2016/Welcome/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mfgaspar.github.io/index.html//2016/Welcome/</guid>
        
        <category>Cooking Analytics</category>
        
        
        <category>Cooking Analytics</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
